Petros Angelatos

https://github.com/petrosagg|Barcelona, Spain|petrosagg@gmail.com

Summary

In the past 9 years I co-founded balena.io, designed and built its software architecture, grew the company to 100 people, and raised over \$14M in funding. During this time I developed deep expertise in multiple areas ranging from web technologies, microservices, database and API design to the Linux operating system, systems programming, and embedded devices.

Experience

balena.io (<u>website</u>) / Founder & CTO

FEBRUARY 2012 - NOVEMBER 2020, LONDON & SEATTLE

Complete set of tools for building, deploying, and managing fleets of connected Linux devices with over 150k active devices on the platform.

Engineering Management

- Managed diverse, remote engineering team of 50 people
- Conducted hundreds of interviews and grew team from 3 to 50 engineers
- Led the architecture of the product spanning hardware design, operating systems, backend & network architecture, API design, frontend architecture
- Scaled infrastructure, supporting exponential product and usage growth
- Led several R&D breakthroughs and their path to production

Technical Expertise

- Frontend React, HTML5, CSS, WebGL, Incremental Computation

- API Design REST, GraphQL, OData

- Monitoring SLAs, Performance metrics, Prometheus, Netdata

- Security TLS, JWT, OAuth, Browser Sandbox, Cryptographic Principles

- Databases Data modelling, Normalization, Indexing, SQL, Datalog

- **Scaling** Sharding, Replication, Caching, CAP, CRDTs

- Containers docker, runc, systemd-nspawn, k8s

Infrastructure AWS (incl VPC, EKS, S3, RDS, IAM), CI/CD, Jenkins
Networking OpenVPN, TCP/IP, DNS, Avahi, DHCP, ARP, NTP
Linux Filesystems, cgroups, namespaces, systemd

- **Embedded** I²C, SPI, GPIOs, DTBs, FCC certification, Schematic review

Notable R&D Results

Docker on ARM (blog post)

First port and public release of Docker on the ARM architecture

Schedule Optimization with Linear Programming (blog post)

Modelled our company meeting requirements as a set of constraints and used linear programming to find the optimal schedule

Docker ARM emulation on x86 (blog post)

Patched QEMU for transparent ARM emulation on x86 and integrated it with the Dockerfile build process

NodeJS Linux LKL (github repo)

NodeJS native bindings to Linux kernel instance running in userspace. Allows manipulating Linux filesystems from any operating system

balenaEngine (website)

- Hardened docker engine against power offs and intermittent network
- Optimised IO operations during pulling to minimise flash wear
- Shrunk binary size by 75% for space constrained devices

Docker binary deltas (blog post, presentation)

- Implemented librsync based docker image delta algorithm
- Up to 70x less bandwidth transferred over the wire

Kamibu Ltd / Founder & Software Engineer

DECEMBER 2010 - JANUARY 2012 - ATHENS, GREECE

Worked with a small team to build FinalPromise, a browser-based 3D MMORPG

- FinalEngine (github repo)
 - Implemented JavaScript 3D renderer on top of WebGL

- Implemented a high performance JavaScript physics engine
- XSTEER (promo video)
 - Implemented mobile application that streamed a phone's IMU sensors in real-time over the local network to allow controlling web based games with a joystick experience

Zino (archived git repo) / Software Engineer

DECEMBER 2008 - DECEMBER 2010, ATHENS, GREECE

Greek social network for teenagers

- Feature development in HTML/CSS/PHP/JavaScript
- Implemented realtime chat and presence server in NodeJS 0.4

Conferences

balenaEngine: a Moby based container engine for IoT / Dockercon

NOVEMBER 2017, COPENHAGEN

- Presented the binary space saving techniques and binary delta algorithm used in balenaEngine. (video)

Bringing DevOps to Devices - Modern Update Approaches for Embedded Linux / ELC MAY 2016, SAN DIEGO, CA

- State of the art overview of remote update strategies on embedded devices (video)

Introducing resinOS: An Operating System Tailored for Containers and Built for the Embedded World / ELCE

OCTOBER 2016, BERLIN

- Presented techniques used in resinOS for multi-board compatibility, minimal footprint, and robust remote updates (video)

Running ARM containers on x86 platforms / FOSSCOMM

APRIL 2016, ATHENS

- Presented the inner workings of QEMU ARM emulation during a x86 docker build

P2P Web Video Conferencing / FOSSCOMM

JUNE 2010, ATHENS

- Presented the state of the art on peer to peer browser connections, covering UDP hole punching and NAT traversal

Teaching

Web Development Class (website)

SEPTEMBER 2010 - JANUARY 2011, ATHENS

Semester long Web Development class. Taught 200 university students HTML, CSS, Javascript, PHP, MySQL.

Security Class (website)

MAY 2014, ATHENS

Broad security seminar on web application security, HTTPS, cryptography, GPG, Tor, OTR, and Bitcoin.

Education

National Technical University of Athens

SEPTEMBER 2008 - SEPTEMBER 2010 (DROP OUT), ATHENS

Electrical and Computer Engineering

Programming Languages

10+ years of JavaScript, NodeJS, Python

6+ years of Golang 4+ years of Rust

Languages

English: Fluent Speaker **Spanish**: Intermediate

Greek: Native Speaker